A Guide to the Milka T. Bliznakov Papers and Architectural Drawings, 1946-2010
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Milka T. Bliznakov Papers and Architectural Drawings,
1946-2010
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1991-025
26.0 cu. ft. 31 boxes; 6 oversize; 4 artifacts
Milka Bliznakov was a Bulgarian architect, architectural historian, and professor who practiced in Bulgaria, France, and the United States. The collection consists of her publications, research, correspondence, professional documentation of her practice, conference participation materials, teaching materials, and documents related to her involvement as the founder of the International Archive of Women in Architecture.
Bliznakov, Milka T., 1927-2010
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Milka T. Bliznakov Papers and Architectural Drawings Collection was donated to the IAWA at Special Collections in 2002 by Dr. Milka Bliznakov. Additions were made to the collection by Milka Bliznakov and Donna Dunay in 2006, 2007, 2011, and 2015.
Biographical Information
Milka Bliznakov was born in Varna, Bulgaria in 1927. She attended the State Polytechnic Institute of Sofia and graduated with a master's degree in architecture in 1951. Bliznakov began practicing architecture in Bulgaria in 1952. In 1959, Bliznakov moved her practice to France. Two years later, Bliznakov emigrated to the United States.During her first years in the United States, Bliznakov worked as an architect and studied Soviet architecture. She earned her Ph.D in architectural history from Columbia University in 1971. She taught at the University of Texas from 1972-1974, where she co-founded the Institute of Modern Russian Culture.
In 1974, Milka Bliznakov became a professor at Virginia Polytechnic Insitute and State University's College of Architecture and Urban Planning, where she taught in the urban design program. Bliznakov became an authority on the Russian avante-garde and constructivism movements. In 1985, Bliznakov worked with the Virginia Tech University Libraries and the College of Architecture and Urban Studies to establish the International Archive of Women in Architecture. She served as the chair of the IAWA Board of Advisors from 1985-1993. Milka Bliznakov retired in 1998 in conjunction with the establishment of the Milka Bliznakov Prize. The Milka Bliznakov Prize is awarded annually to those whose research furthers the knowledge of women's contributions to architecture and design. Bliznakov continued to acquire and donate works to the IAWA until her death on November 4, 2010.
Scope and Content
This collection documents the activities of Milka Bliznakov (1927-2010), the founder of the International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA) and former chair of its board of advisors (1985-1993). It contains personal materials, including biographical information and personal correspondence. This collection also contains materials documenting Milka's prolific career as an architect and a professor emerita at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Some significant topics represented in these files are avante-garde architecture; Russian constructivism; futurist architecture in the Soviet Union; the history of Bulgaria and Bulgarian architecture; and women in art and architecture. In addition, this collection contains unique documents about the destruction of architectural structures in Croatia during the Bosnian war; Federal Broadcast Information Service (FBIS) reports on Soviet concentration camps; and detailed drawings and and project plans for Soviet infastructure. This collection also documentsd the proceedings of organizations and conferences attended by Milka Bliznakov such as L'Union Internationale des Femmes Architectes (UIFA), the International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA), and the Association for Slavic, Eastern European, and Eurasian Studies (AAASS). Materials are largely textual, comprising of correspondence, memoranda, minutes and agendas, legal materials, clippings, publications, reference files, blueprints, and maps. Among other formats scattered throughout the collection are photographs, negatives, and artifacts such as plaques. This collection also includes detailed drawings and specifications from Milka Bliznakov's architecture practice.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into five broad series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Faculty Papers, Major Projects, and Art & Artifacts. Within each of series, materials are arranged according to original order and chronology. Where original order was not clear, processing staff used the Standard Series for Architecture and Landscape Design Records as guidance.
Separated Materials
Two volumes were returned to the Library of Columbia University. The following books were separated from the collection to be cataloged for the Rare Book Collection:
Watkins, R.N. The Ideal Communist City. New York: Braziller, 1968.
Lloyd, P. & Collie, K. San Francisco: a guide to recent architecture. London: Ellipsis, 1997.
Markelin, U. Profiles: Pioneering Women Architects from Finland. Museum of Finnish Architecture, 1983.
Use of Tradition in Russian & Soviet Architecture, guest edited by Cooke, C. & Kudriavtsev, A. Architectural Design journal, v. 57, no. 7/8. London: Architectural Design, 1987.
Brumfield, W.C. Reshaping Russian Architecture: Western Technology, Utopian Dreams. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1990.
Somaya, B., Mehta, U., & Hecar Foundation. An Emancipated Place: the proceedings of the conference and exhibitino held in Mumbai, February 2000. Mumbai: Hecar Foundation, 2000.
Kuperus, M., & Meinsma, H.C. Architectes. Amsterdam: Uitgeverij Thoth, 1990.
Boutelle, S.H. & Morgan, J. Julia Morgan, Architect. New York: Abbeville Press, 1988.
Poem about Trees. (ISBN: 9785090245890),
The American Glossary of Architectural Terms.
Illustrated Garnsey.
La Realidad Sovietica.
Construction and Reconstruction of Towns.
Working Architectural Studios I-Design Department of the Moscow Soviet.
Working Architectural Studios II-Design Department of the Moscow Soviet.
Russian Formalism.
Blacksburg (Va.); Faculty; History of Women in Architecture; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); University History; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Women architects--Bulgaria; Women--History
- Series I. Personal Papers, 1951-2011; Box
  Scope and Content
  This series includes Milka Bliznakov's biographical information, personal correspondence, travel, photographs, and other personal documents. Noteworthy objects include a video cassette on Milka Bliznakov, a stock certificate, and correspondence regarding the destruction of Croatian architecture during the Yugoslav Wars.
  - Bliznakov, M. Citizen Forum - Panel Video Casette, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Information, 1995-2011; This file consists of Bliznakov's resumes, curriculum vitae, biographies, and obituaries. In addition, this file contains a memorial written by Anna Sokolina in both Russian and English. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1975-2006; Christmas cards, postcards, and letters from Milka's friends, family, and colleagues. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Travel, 1973-n.d.; File contains post cards from Milka Bliznakov's travel and a booklet from the Mongolian National Tourist Organization. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, 1951-2000; Photographs and film negatives from Bliznakov's graduation from the State Polytechnic University in Sofia (1951), a wedding in Bulgaria, a trip to Romania (1998), and the Hilde Westrom Exhibit photographs (2000). (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Pacific American Group, Inc. Stock Certificate, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Series II. Professional Papers, 1926, 1960-2009; Box
  This series consists of correspondence, writings, presentations, associations and committees, awards, research notes, reference files, and other professional works by Milka Bliznakov. These materials reflect Milka's work as a professor and architectural historian at Virginia Tech, as well as her broader network of women in architecture through the IAWA. Other noteworthy items include Milka's portfolio of work and exhibition posters collected from events.
  - Subseries a. Correspondence, 1973-2005
    - Correspondence re: The Destruction of Croatian Monuments, 1991; This file contains two letters from Dr. Sena Sekulic-Gvozdanovic, a professor at the University of Zagreb in Croatia. This file contains documentation of Croatian architecture and its destruction. In addition, the file contains a letter from the University of Zagreb's architecture faculty. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Professional Correspondence (1999-2002) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Professional Correspondence (1979-1987) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Alonso, Carmen Espegel, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brians, Audrey L. - Milka (1977-2002), This file contains correspondence between Brians and Bliznakov. In addition, this file contains pamphlets entitled "Women in American Architecture: A Historical and Contemporary Perspective" and "Architecture: Women in the Profession", postcards, and photographs of Brians. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bulant-Kamenova, Aneta - Milka (2003), This file contains a curriculum vitae for Aneta Bulant-Kamenova and a letter in Bulgarian to Milka. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Galster, Gertrud Klinge - Milka, 2002; This file contains a letter and photographs. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Gottlieb, Lois D. - Milka (2003), This file contains photographs from Gotlieb. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Hansen, Fani - Milka, n.d.; This file contains a postcard from Hansen to Bliznakov. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Hastings, L. Jane - Milka (2002-2003), This file contains a Christmas card from the Hastings family. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Higashi, Yumiko Osawa - Milka (2001) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Perkins, Nancy - Milka (2003), This file contains correspondence with Nancy Perkins regarding Anna W. Keichline. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Kruger, Eva - Milka, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Nation, Shelagh - Milka (2002) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Roth, Maria - Milka (2003) (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Stratigakos, Despina - Milka (2003) (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Von Der Weppen, Maria - Milka, 2003; This file contains a letter from Vonder Weppen and photographs. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Willis, Beverly- Milka (2001-2002) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Van Hook, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Balke, Thomas, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Schmidt-Thomsen, Helga, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - van Ginkel, Blanche Lemco, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Lang, Evelyn - Milka, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - McDonald, Roxana, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - The Boston Society of Architects (1990) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Society of Architectural Historians (1975) (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Slavic Review (1973) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Ojai House Plans, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Subseries b. Writings, 1967-1998
    - From Theory to Practice in Constructivist Architecture (1979) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Women in Architectural Profession (1985) (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Soviet Women Architects (1917-1967), Biographical guide to Soviet women in architecture. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Space is the Medium of Architecture (1990) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Futurist Architecture-Russia, n.d.; This file contains Soviet architectural papers and city planning projects such as the flying city project. In addition, this file contains Milka Bliznakov's academic papers entitled "The City of Futurists" and "Design Plans for Moscow". (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Western Technology and Soviet Avante-garde Architecture, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Bibliography of Bulgarian Architects, n.d.; This file contains a bibliographic aid compiled by Milka Bliznakov on Bulgarian architects. The aid was requested by the Library of Congress on slavic architects. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Styles and Techniques in Bulgarian Folk Architecture, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bulgarian Urbanization, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - National Aspects of Bulgarian Architecture, n.d.; This file contains two academic papers written by Milka Bliznakov: "National Aspects of Bulgarian Architecture" and "New Towns in Soviet Asia: A Method for Industrialization and Population Resettlement". (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Vision, Art, and Architecture (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - From Theory to Practice in Constructivist Architecture (1979) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - The Constructivist Movement in Architecture, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Exhibition Reviews on Structurism, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Urban Planning Theories in the USSR, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Geometry in Modern Architecture, n.d.; This file contains a pamphlet and academic paper on geometry in modern architecture. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Geometric Abstraction, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Architecture and Technology (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Soviet Formalism, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Ladovski Paper, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Malevich Paper, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Bulgarian Art & Architecture of the 20th Century: the Development of a Regional Culture (folder 1 of 4), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 16-19)
    - Negatives for Bulgarian Art & Architecture, n.d.; This file contains negatives for Milka Bliznakov's paper entitled "Bulgarian Art & Architecture of the 20th Century: the Development of a Regional Culture". (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Ladovski Drafts, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Three Makers of Modern Architecture and the Thoughts that Shaped Them (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Art, Perception, and the Education of Vision (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - From Theory to Practice in Constructivist Architecture (folder 1 of 2), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5, Folder 4)
    - Part IV: The Culture of Technocracy (folder 1 of 2), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6, Folder 7)
    - Part III: A Post Modernism Named Socialist Realism (folder 1 of 2), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8, Folder 9)
    - Review of Profession, Cadre, or Academy, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Modern Architecture in the USSR, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Science & Technology, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Soviet Women Architects, n.d.; This file contains a bibliographical guide to Soviet women architects from 1917-1937. (Box 3, Folder 14, Folder 13)
    - New Towns in Soviet Asia, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 16, Folder 15)
    - City of the Russian Futurists, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - The Contributions of Women to the Avante-garde Architecture in Russia, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Women in the Architectural Profession, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Women Architects from Eastern Europe, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Ladovski Publication, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - From Theory to Practice in Constructivist Architecture, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Postscript, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - New Towns on the Baykal-Amur Mainline, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Women Architects in Eastern Europe, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Soviet Housing During the Experimental Years (1918-1933), 1992 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Soviet Avante-garde Architecture: New York Exhibitions of the Twenties, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Publications, 1978-1996 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Zinaida Fedorovna Zhuchenko Gerngross, 1993; This file contains a paper written by Milka Bliznakov on Zinaida Fedorovna Zhuchenko-Gerngross, a female tsarist spy from (1880-1903). Zinaida infiltrated revolutionary groups for the tsar's royal police force. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Urban Planning in the USSR: Integrative Theories, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Ladovskii: The Search for Rational Science of Architecture, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Suprematism in Architecture, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The City of Russian Futurists, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - New Towns on the BAM, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries c. Presentations, 1983-1999
    - Yale Lectures, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Architecture of a Totalitarian State, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Tech Symposium on Women in Design and Architecture (Box 4, Folder 9, Folder 8)
    - Modern Architecture in the Twenties in Russia, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Research and Presentations, 1988-1999; This file contains various reports, pamphlets, and flyers for Milka Bliznakov's presentations spanning from 1988-1999. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Subseries d. Associations and Committees, 1963-2009
    - 1988-UIFA Congress, Washington D.C., This file contains information from the 8th UIFA Congress. In addition, this file contains reports written by female architects on significant architectural topics and Milka Bliznakov's correspondence with colleagues. (Box 4, Folder 13, Folder 14, Folder 12)
    - 1991-UIFA Congress, Copenhagen, Denmark (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - 1993-UIFA Congress, South Africa (Box 4, Folder 16, Folder 17)
    - 1996-UIFA Congress, Budapest, Hungary (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - UIFA Miscellaneous, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous, 1963-2005; This file contains records, brochures, and newsletters from various conferences. In addition, this file contains correspondence regarding the IAWA (1989). This file also contains information on the Beverly Willis Foundation. (Box 4, Folder 20-21, 27)
    - IAWA: Administrative Notes, 2005-2007; This file contains correspondence with the association, donor information, and member information. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - IAWA: Financial Information, 2004-2009; This file contains information on the Bliznakov award and information on IAWA stakeholders. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - IAWA: Proposal, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - International Community Development Associates, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Second World Congress on Soviet East European Studies, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - 1988 National Convention-AAASS (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Architectural Societies, 1972-1981 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Women East-West, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - International Club, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - 1994 Conference Leadership Through Design (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Ferrari Symposium II Convergence, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Subseries e. Awards, 1960-2003
    - Virginia Tech Ten Year Service Award, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Virginia Tech Twenty Year Service Award, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - The Marquis Who's Who Awards, 1979-2001 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Institute for Urban Design, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - The Parthena Award (1994) (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - The New York Academy of Sciences (1994) (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - National Geographic Society, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Union of Bulgarian Architects, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Sixth International DOCOMOMO Conference, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Professional Seminar Consultants, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - International Academy of Architecture, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Wall of Tolerance, 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Planned Parenthood Certificate of Appreciation, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - CAB-membership, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Republican National Committee: Presidebtial Achievement Award, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - International Research & Exchanges Board, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Certificate to Practice Architecture, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - William Kinne Fellows Memorial Scholarship, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Professor Emeritus of Architecture, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Tau Sigma Delta, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Woman of the Year (2001) (Folder 4)
    - Advisor Emerita of the IAWA (2001) (Folder 4)
    - Awards and Certificates from Columbia, 1968-1971; This file contains a certificate of Milka's recommendation for a doctorate of philosophy (1969), a commencement reception invitation (1971), Milka Blizankov's New York license to practice architecture (1968, 1972), commencement program (1971), William Kline Fellows summer scholarship (1970), and commencement certificates from Colombia (1971). (Folder 4)
    - Sofia Graduation Certificate (1960) (Folder 4)
    - Virginia Tech Awards (1990-1997), 1990, 1996-1997; This file contains Milka Blizankov's 15 years of service award (1990) and Milka Bliznakov's retirement certificate (1996). (Folder 4)
  - Subseries f. Research Notes, 1984-1990
    - Bulgarian Chronology, 1984; This file contains Milka Bliznakov's handwritten and typed notes on the chronology of Bulgaria. In addition, this file contains articles that were included with Milka's notes. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Bulgarian Architecture, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bulgarian Palaces, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Bulgarian Folklore, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Hotel de Soubise, n.d.; This file includes Milka's manuscript on French architecture and an article written on French architecture. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subseries g. Reference Files, 1926-1998
    - Intermediate Zones in Modern Architecture, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Newsletters on Women in Art, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Dumont A. Paintures, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Bulgaria-Urban Development (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Photographs of Soviet Urban Design, This file contains negative on urban desing in the Soviet Union. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Utopian Dreams, This file contains photographs depicting site plans. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - For Housing Book, n.d.; This file contains photographs depicting city design plans for the USSR. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Soviet Women Architects, 1975-1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Bulgarian Papers, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Tsarist Russia and Balkan Nationalism, 1984; This file contains an article on Russian influence on the affairs of Bulgaria and Serbia (1879-1886). (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Impressions from Palestine, 1926; This file includes an article entitled "Impressions from Palestine" written in Buglarian. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Collection of Folklore and Ethnography, 1936; This file contains an article on folklore and ethnography from a Bulgarian academic journal. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1983-1988 (Box 5, Folder 18, Folder 19)
    - Women in the Arts, 1927-1996 (Box 5, Folder 20-25)
    - Soviet Concentration Camps, 1955-1981; This file contains documents documents regarding Soviet concentration camps. It contains reports from the Foreign Broadcast Information Broadcast (FBIS) and additional reports in both English and Russian. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Photos of Bulgarian Architecture (color), n.d.
    - Photos of Bulgarian Architecture (black & white), n.d.
    - AAASS 1988 Meeting Hawaii, This file contains newsletters and articles regarding the AAASS 1998 meeting. (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
    - Articles on Soviet Design, 1927-1973; This file contains articles and photographs on Soviet design. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Andrei Ikonnikov, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - The City and Architecture of Sofia, Bulgaria (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Land Commune and Peasant Community in Russia, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Architects of Puerto Rico, the Caribbean, and Florida and their Work, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Factors in the Career Choices of Women in Environmental Design, 1977; This file contains a working paper written by Alan G. Winslow. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - The Structurist, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Soviet Union Vol 5, Part 2 1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Supplemental Curriculum for Urban Design: The UCLA Experiment (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - The Blacksburg Town Zoning Orginance, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Lanthrop Douglass F.A.I.A. Architect, 1968; This file contains copies of photographs and sketches of architectural plans. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - From Chaos to Creation (1972-1992) (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Women Architects in Austria (1900-1987), 1987-1988 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - The 'New Build' of the Twenties and the Development of a Functionalist Kitchen, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 19)